AVINASH ANAND AHUJA

505 S Race St, Urbana, IL-61801 Ph: (217) 819-9001 aaahuja2@illinois.edu http://avinashahuja.me

SUMMARY

I am passionate about Applied Data Science and solving problems in the areas of Open Governance and Data Access & Transparency. I have experience in applying **Machine Learning** and **NLP** to challenging and socially relevant problems.

EDUCATION

University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign Illinois, USA

Master of Science in **Computer Science** *KDD 2016 – Student Travel Award*

Master of Science in Civil Engineering

August 2015 - May 2017

GPA: 3.84/4.0

August 2013 - May 2015

GPA: 3.87/4.0

WORK EXPERIENCE

Data Science Intern, Anheuser-Busch InBev, Champaign IL

May 2016 - Present

- Applying Active Learning and Hierarchical Clustering to meld retailer data from multiple sources.
- Building a forecasting model and recommendation engine for businesses to optimize purchase quantities.

Summer Fellow, Data Science for Social Good (DSSG), University of Chicago

May 2015 - August 2015

- Applied ML and NLP to create metrics on dynamics of skills and jobs in the American economy.
- Collaborated with government agencies and non-profits to understand requirements and identify important metrics.
- Developed scalable data processing pipeline using Spark and AWS.

Senior Engineer, Larsen & Toubro (L&T), Modular Fabrication Yard, Oman

Sept. 2011 to July 2013

- Planned, executed and monitored fabrication of Oil Rigs (3000+ Tons).
- Designed and developed automated report generation systems.

PROJECTS

Object Detection and Tracking in 3D, University of Illinois

Spring 2016

- Almost real-time drone localization in 3D using consumer grade webcams.
- Improved detection using SVM w/ hard negative mining.

Automatic Extraction of Product Features and Sentiments from Amazon Reviews, University of Illinois

Fall 2015

- Experimented with supervised and unsupervised ML to identify key product features.
- Visualize feedback for designers using **Python + Django** to assist in improvement of product.

Identifying Skills Gap in Chicago's Labor Market, DSSG

Summer 2015

- Developed a **Data Driven approach** to analyze **skills gap** in Chicago's labor market.
- Prototyped a scalable data pipeline using AWS, PostgreSQL and Apache Spark and frontend with Python + Flask.

Predicting partners in International Trade Networks, University of Illinois

Fall 2014

- Applied community detection in International Trade network
- Trained SVM on existing trade agreements to predict future beneficial trade agreements.

3DThermography using Kinect and Thermal camera, University of Illinois

Spring 2014

- Developed a prototype product to generate 3D models of buildings with temperature information.
- Aimed to improve energy audit of buildings, reduce environmental footprint and energy costs.

RELEVENT COURSES

- Machine Learning
 NLP
 Data Driven Design
 Computer Vision
 Algorithms
 Cloud Computing
- High Performance Computing
 Social and Economic Networks
 Optimization and Decision making

SOFTWARE SKILLS

- Languages: Python, Ruby, SQL, C/C++
- Frameworks/Libraries: Flask/Django, Rails, Hadoop/Hive, Spark

Packages: MATLAB, Mathematica, R, Primavera

MEMBERSHIPS AND ACTIVITIES

Chapter President, Asha for Education, University of Illinois Chapter **Student Advisor**, Centre for Innovation in Teaching & Learning (**CITL**), University of Illinois **Treasurer and Web Developer**, Asha for Education, University of Illinois Chapter

Aug. 2015 – Present

Feb. 2015 – July 2015 Aug. 2014 – July 2015